<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indexing>
 <paragraph index="13" node_type="writer">	</paragraph>
 <object index="26" name="Table3" object_type="table"/>
 <paragraph index="28" node_type="writer" parent_index="26">United States and Canada </paragraph>
 <paragraph index="34" node_type="writer" parent_index="26">GPM Monitoring</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="40" node_type="writer" parent_index="26">April 18, 2025</paragraph>
 <object index="45" name="Table2" object_type="table"/>
 <paragraph index="47" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">United States </paragraph>
 <paragraph index="48" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Bottom line. While the 90-day pause in reciprocal tariff implementation has brought some relief to financial markets, surveys of economic activity and expectations continue to show deterioration -this week through the BoA’s Fund Manager’s Survey, and the Manufacturing surveys by the Philadelphia and NY Feds.  Further, the Fed’s chairman hinted this week at a potential stagflationary scenario in the coming months. The chairman also casted doubt on the notion that tariffs will imply only a “one time” surge in inflation. Meanwhile, other high frequency releases remain within normal ranges so far. We hold our tracking at -0.3%ar in Q1.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="49" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Policy </paragraph>
 <paragraph index="50" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Trade: Last Friday, semiconductor exemptions built into the reciprocal tariffs were “clarified”, affecting approximately 22% of Chinese imports to the US). This lowered the tariff on items like smartphones from 145% to 20%, the baseline for China since March 4. This clarification impacted roughly 3% of US imports and lowered the average US tariff for China from 145 to approx. 115. It also lowered the US average tariff from approximately from 30 to 26.5 percent while China’s retaliatory tariff on the US currently remains at 125 pct.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="51" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Semiconductors from China will be tariffed, nonetheless, (perhaps within 2 months) under the Fentanyl-war regime currently used to tariff aluminum, steel and automobiles. Also, more built-in exceptions to the reciprocal tariff regime may be soon clarified: Lumber, copper, pharmaceuticals, bullion, energy and critical minerals.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="53" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Monetary: At the same time, Fed Chairman Powell has hinted in a speech Wednesday that the Fed may have to confront the dual challenge of elevated inflation and output slowdown. The chairman also cast doubt on the notion that tariffs will imply only a “one time” surge in inflation. The Fed is widely expected to hold policy rate unchanged on the May 6 FOMC meeting.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="55" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Surveys of Activity and Expectations</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="57" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">The Philadelphia Fed Manufacturing Index was -26.4 in April 2025, down from 12.5 in March, substantially below market expectations of 2 pointing to the largest decline in regional economic activity since April 2023. The survey’s new orders index dropped sharply from 8.7 in March to -34.2 in April, marking its lowest level since April 2020. Meanwhile, the shipments index declined by 11 points to -9.1. The future activity indicators continued to suggest subdued expectations for growth over the next six months.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="59" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">While the NY Fed’s Empire State Manufacturing Index rose to -8.1 in April 2025 from -20 in March (the lowest since May 2023), the future general business conditions index fell to -7.4, its second lowest reading on record.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="61" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Bank of America’s monthly Fund manager’s survey for March showed investor sentiment regarding economic prospects is, in summary, the most negative in three decades. That pessimism isn’t yet fully reflected in their asset allocation, which could mean more losses for US stocks. The survey also showed that 1 year expectations of global inflation have also risen among the nearly 205 institutional fund managers interviewed.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="63" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Official Data Releases</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="64" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">U.S. import prices slipped 0.1% in March 2025 (against consensus of 0%) driven by a 2.3% drop in fuel prices and moderate increases in the other categories. Note that the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics’ Import and Export Price Indexes exclude tariffs.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="66" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Census Bureau’s retail sales (Chart D) increased strongly (1.4% MoM) in March, slightly above consensus (1.3%). Sales growth was above average for motor vehicles and parts (5.3%) building material and garden equipment (3.3%); sporting goods, hobby, musical instrument, and book stores (2.4%); food services e drinking places (1.8%) while gasoline sales dropped.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="67" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">The surge in autos was expected as part of the “tariff frontrunning” phenomenon sparked by the 25% tariffs on all foreign-made vehicles brought into the US that kicked in on April 3. This surge will partly continue into April given that auto parts tariffs will only take effect on May 3 (potentially net of some new exemptions that have been hinted at by the President).</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="68" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">The stable components of retail sales that enter the calculation of GDP (control measure) only increased at 0.4 percent mom, however, below expectations of 0.6.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="70" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Housing starts (Chart A), a volatile indicator, dropped sharply in March (-11.4% mom sa) below consensus (-5% mom sa) following a large increase of (9.8% mom sa) in February. At the same time building permits increased (1.6% mom sar), following a contraction in February (-1% mom sar).</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="72" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Initial jobless claims this week equaled (215,000), somewhat below consensus (225,000).</paragraph>
 <object index="81" name="Table1" object_type="table"/>
 <paragraph index="83" node_type="writer" parent_index="81">Chart A:  Housing starts dropped sharply in the context of a highly volatile series.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="86" node_type="writer" parent_index="81">Chart D:  Retail sales rebounded in March, driven by automobile sales, while the control measure declined.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="89" node_type="writer" parent_index="81">s.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="102" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Upcoming releases:  Thursday: March Durable Goods Orders, March Existing Home Sales.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="103" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Canada</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="104" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">The Consumer Price Index in Canada increased 0.30 percent MoM in March of 2025 below consensus of 0.6, driven by low gasoline price growth. The core CPI increased by 0.1 MoM, dropping from 0.7% in February.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="106" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Also, the Bank of Canada held its benchmark interest rate unchanged at 2.75%, the first hold following 2.25 percentage points of cuts in seven consecutive decisions.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="107" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Forecast implications. We hold our tracking for Q1 at 1.9%ar (WEO Live 1.0%ar), given the strong start of year outturns for monthly GDP. Our tracking is consistent with stalling monthly GDP growth in March, following the weak outturn in February. However, we continue to expect a contraction in activity in Q2.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="108" node_type="writer" parent_index="45">Upcoming releases:    Friday: Retail Sales Feb., Retail Sales Prel. Mar.</paragraph>
 <object alt="" name="Picture 5" object_type="graphic"/>
 <object alt="" name="Picture 3" object_type="graphic"/>
</indexing>
